<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Terminal</title>
    <link>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Terminal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 18:00:51 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://leonorae.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update</title>
      <link>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/week-3-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 18:00:51 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/week-3-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I researched the available causal reasoning packages for Python, primarily DoWhy, CausalNex, EconML, as well as some preliminary research into more specialized packages such as scikit-uplift. I also researched available datasets related to the field. Most of the datasets are related to econometrics or medical outcomes, expectedly. I learned that some of the datasets available on PhysioNet require credentialled access, and I’m unsure if I would be able to (or if it would even be worth it) to acquire it for this class. I wrote and posted my project proposal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I researched the available causal reasoning packages for Python, primarily DoWhy, CausalNex, EconML, as well as some preliminary research into more specialized packages such as scikit-uplift. I also researched available datasets related to the field. Most of the datasets are related to econometrics or medical outcomes, expectedly. I learned that some of the datasets available on PhysioNet require credentialled access, and I’m unsure if I would be able to (or if it would even be worth it) to acquire it for this class. I wrote and posted my project proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal website is up at leonorae.github.io, but I need to add more of the required pages, which I will work on this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I will also do some &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; type examples with the packages mentioned above as well as some groundwork theoretical research and present some examples from both in a post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main impediments at this time are organizational, I need to outline my time and schedule around heavy weeks in Systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can improve my process this week by organizing my time in regards to working on my project and doing &amp;ldquo;logistical&amp;rdquo; things such as reflecting on my work in posts more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 4 Update</title>
      <link>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/week-4-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 18:06:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/week-4-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;knowledge-update&#34;&gt;Knowledge Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned about the overall process of creating a causal model, estimation of causal effect, inference, refutation tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://causalwizard.app/inference/article/causal-diagram&#34;&gt;causal diagram is essentially a prior assumption&lt;/a&gt; that is somewhat subjective. This reinforces my prior assumption that I should choose a relatively well understood, normalized, and simple dataset(s), because it would be difficult to generalize and construct complex causal models for domains I am speculating about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was very curious about the idea of &amp;ldquo;discovering&amp;rdquo; causal effects from essentially unstructured data, but I will assume that this is not a basic topic and leave it to research after this project has helped me to understand the basics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;knowledge-update&#34;&gt;Knowledge Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned about the overall process of creating a causal model, estimation of causal effect, inference, refutation tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://causalwizard.app/inference/article/causal-diagram&#34;&gt;causal diagram is essentially a prior assumption&lt;/a&gt; that is somewhat subjective. This reinforces my prior assumption that I should choose a relatively well understood, normalized, and simple dataset(s), because it would be difficult to generalize and construct complex causal models for domains I am speculating about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was very curious about the idea of &amp;ldquo;discovering&amp;rdquo; causal effects from essentially unstructured data, but I will assume that this is not a basic topic and leave it to research after this project has helped me to understand the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-update&#34;&gt;Code Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Established that I will focus on using &lt;code&gt;dowhy&lt;/code&gt; first, implement &lt;code&gt;causalnex&lt;/code&gt; primarily as a comparison, use &lt;code&gt;econml&lt;/code&gt; for&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Proposal</title>
      <link>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/project-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 18:41:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/project-proposal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-proposal&#34;&gt;Project Proposal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;causal-inference-pipeline-with-api&#34;&gt;Causal Inference Pipeline with API&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vision-statement&#34;&gt;Vision Statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Causal inference is a technique that is important in the history of artificial
intelligence. It is interested in finding causes and effects from data and
constructing causal models. It is a difficult problem for many reasons, including
the classic &amp;ldquo;coorelation does not imply causation&amp;rdquo; problem. A ground truth is often
difficult to find, and experimenting/gathering many kinds of data can be difficult
or impossible.
It is related to the field of econometrics, and is important to the medical field
in assessing causes of patient outcomes.
I would like to explore the current state of the field using Python libraries,
developing a basic pipeline and experimenting with various techniques and datasets,
and ultimately deliver a functional API.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-proposal&#34;&gt;Project Proposal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;causal-inference-pipeline-with-api&#34;&gt;Causal Inference Pipeline with API&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vision-statement&#34;&gt;Vision Statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Causal inference is a technique that is important in the history of artificial
intelligence. It is interested in finding causes and effects from data and
constructing causal models. It is a difficult problem for many reasons, including
the classic &amp;ldquo;coorelation does not imply causation&amp;rdquo; problem. A ground truth is often
difficult to find, and experimenting/gathering many kinds of data can be difficult
or impossible.
It is related to the field of econometrics, and is important to the medical field
in assessing causes of patient outcomes.
I would like to explore the current state of the field using Python libraries,
developing a basic pipeline and experimenting with various techniques and datasets,
and ultimately deliver a functional API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to learn more about Bayes Nets and causal theory while gaining
practical software development experience. I would like to gain an understanding of
the available python packages related to these topics and be able to explain their
differences and compatabilities. I need to gain experience with project design and
management. I think it will be a good experience to document my project as I work
on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;goals--milestones&#34;&gt;Goals / Milestones&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement a basic causal inference pipeline with example data using causal
inference python packages. Document experience and reasoning for choices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outcome: gain knowledge of the state of existing causal inference packages
(egs. DoWhy, CausalNex, EconML)
in python, including tradeoffs/benefits of packages not used for the implementation
of the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a basic API for the pipeline using &lt;code&gt;fastapi&lt;/code&gt;. Verify that it works with
tests. Keep it updated as the pipeline and data change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outcome: gain experience with API implementation and maintenence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a more advanced causal inference pipeline with a real world (or
synthetic approximation) dataset and additional functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outcome: gain knowledge of causal inference techniques and results,
research experience, and development experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;risks-and-mitigation-strategies&#34;&gt;Risks and Mitigation Strategies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overwhelming theoretical background&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will mitigate this by completing a &amp;ldquo;minimum viable&amp;rdquo; pipeline and API before
implementing more advanced techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Problems with data, verification of model performance, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will use a dataset that is tailored for this problem and has had prior
research done on it rather than try to solve a novel problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unforseen difficulty with API, testing, tools, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As said above, I am not setting my research goals too high because I know that
a large part of this project will be about learning methods and tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessments&#34;&gt;Assessments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the weekly writeups, deliver:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;survey of causal reasoning python packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;causal inference pipeline developed with a complex real world or synthetic
dataset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working API access to pipeline with documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 Update</title>
      <link>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/week-2-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 17:42:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/week-2-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week I worked on conceptualizing a project idea, setting up my personal website, and researching the current state of causal inference techniques and libraries. My main struggle with finding a project has been balancing my desire to do open-ended research with the need to create a tangible result which demonstrates my skills. In my introduction post I mentioned my interest in causality, and Professor Guinn suggested a project to create a causal inference pipeline with a library such as DoWhy or CausalNex with a public dataset and make it available as an API-based web service.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This week I worked on conceptualizing a project idea, setting up my personal website, and researching the current state of causal inference techniques and libraries. My main struggle with finding a project has been balancing my desire to do open-ended research with the need to create a tangible result which demonstrates my skills. In my introduction post I mentioned my interest in causality, and Professor Guinn suggested a project to create a causal inference pipeline with a library such as DoWhy or CausalNex with a public dataset and make it available as an API-based web service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like this idea a lot, because it has a good balance of theoretical interest with practicality, as well as a balance of demonstrating/reinforcing skills I have acquired as part of this program with learning new ones. I have created similar models in the Machine Learning class, have used Flask in the Software Development class, etc. but I have not combined the two nor have I done extensive API design. I also like that the minimum viable product seems very attainable, which gives me space to do research on the side and really gain a deep understanding of how the model I create works and experiment with various parameters and techniques. I could also do something like extending the baseline functionality of the API with a natural language interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge I face now is finding a good dataset for the project. In ML I found the majority of publicly available datasets lacking. My interest is in the model architecture itself less than any particular domain, so I will ultimately be looking for something that seems the most likely to contain interesting causal relationships that could be queried. I think I will focus my search on healthcare data first as there is a sizeable medical technology presence in my area and it is a well known application of causal inference and expert system technologies. I may also look into economic data, as the field of econometrics is closely related to ML/causality theory. I am also aware that I do not necessarily have to commit to a single data source at the outset of or for the whole duration of the project, so whatever area I choose I will probably use a smaller dataset or subset while I design the overall pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides looking for potential datasets, this week I need to survey the libraries I will use to implement the model (DoWhy, CausalNex, EconML, scipy/statsmodels, &amp;hellip;?) and web service (Flask/FastAPI, others?). Again I do not think that I have to make a final decision immediately, but rather experiment with all options that seem reasonable and document my findings. From there I should be in a good position to make a decision as my project&amp;rsquo;s subject and goals become more clear. While I know that I work best with a relatively open and flexible approach, I do think that I need to add some structure to my work going forward as compared to this last week. By the end of next week I should also have some general outline of the weekly schedule and deadlines for myself, but allow room for adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 10:12:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://leonorae.github.io/posts/introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first post on my personal website for CSPB 3112.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may add more to it later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This is the first post on my personal website for CSPB 3112.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may add more to it later.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
