<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Terminal</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Terminal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 17:42:21 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 Update</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/week-2-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 17:42:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/week-2-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week I worked on conceptualizing a project idea, setting up my personal website, and researching the current state of causal inference techniques and libraries. My main struggle with finding a project has been balancing my desire to do open-ended research with the need to create a tangible result which demonstrates my skills. In my introduction post I mentioned my interest in causality, and Professor Guinn suggested a project to create a causal inference pipeline with a library such as DoWhy or CausalNex with a public dataset and make it available as an API-based web service.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This week I worked on conceptualizing a project idea, setting up my personal website, and researching the current state of causal inference techniques and libraries. My main struggle with finding a project has been balancing my desire to do open-ended research with the need to create a tangible result which demonstrates my skills. In my introduction post I mentioned my interest in causality, and Professor Guinn suggested a project to create a causal inference pipeline with a library such as DoWhy or CausalNex with a public dataset and make it available as an API-based web service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like this idea a lot, because it has a good balance of theoretical interest with practicality, as well as a balance of demonstrating/reinforcing skills I have acquired as part of this program with learning new ones. I have created similar models in the Machine Learning class, have used Flask in the Software Development class, etc. but I have not combined the two nor have I done extensive API design. I also like that the minimum viable product seems very attainable, which gives me space to do research on the side and really gain a deep understanding of how the model I create works and experiment with various parameters and techniques. I could also do something like extending the baseline functionality of the API with a natural language interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge I face now is finding a good dataset for the project. In ML I found the majority of publicly available datasets lacking. My interest is in the model architecture itself less than any particular domain, so I will ultimately be looking for something that seems the most likely to contain interesting causal relationships that could be queried. I think I will focus my search on healthcare data first as there is a sizeable medical technology presence in my area and it is a well known application of causal inference and expert system technologies. I may also look into economic data, as the field of econometrics is closely related to ML/causality theory. I am also aware that I do not necessarily have to commit to a single data source at the outset of or for the whole duration of the project, so whatever area I choose I will probably use a smaller dataset or subset while I design the overall pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides looking for potential datasets, this week I need to survey the libraries I will use to implement the model (DoWhy, CausalNex, EconML, scipy/statsmodels, &amp;hellip;?) and web service (Flask/FastAPI, others?). Again I do not think that I have to make a final decision immediately, but rather experiment with all options that seem reasonable and document my findings. From there I should be in a good position to make a decision as my project&amp;rsquo;s subject and goals become more clear. While I know that I work best with a relatively open and flexible approach, I do think that I need to add some structure to my work going forward as compared to this last week. By the end of next week I should also have some general outline of the weekly schedule and deadlines for myself, but allow room for adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 10:12:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first post on my personal website for CSPB 3112.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may add more to it later.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This is the first post on my personal website for CSPB 3112.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I may add more to it later.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
